A Finding Aid to the Patricia Jordan Papers, 1870, 1949-1984, in the Archives of American Art AAA.jordpatr
Archives of American Art
Patricia Jordan papers
1870
1949-1984
AAA.jordpatr
Archives of American Art
2.4 Linear feet
The papers of San Francisco based Beat photographer Patricia Jordan measure 2.3 linear feet and date from 1870, 1949-1984. The papers include correspondence, much of it illustrated and with Beat artists and poets, writings, exhibition files, printed materials, photographs, and artwork.
Jordan, Patricia M., 1937-1989
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 6 series
Series 1: Correspondence, circa 1950-1977 (1.1 linear feet; Box 1, OV 4)
Series 2: Writings, circa 1959-1970s (0.1 linear foot; Box 2)
Series 3: Exhibition Files, 1962-1978 (0.1 linear foot; Box 2)
Series 4: Printed Material, circa 1920-1984 (0.2 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 5: Photographs, circa 1870-1970s (0.7 linear feet; Box 2-3)
Series 6: Artwork, 1949-circa 1970s (0.2 linear feet; Box 2-3)
Biographical/Historical note
Patricia Jordan (1937-1988) was a photographer and integral part of the Beat circle in San Francisco during the late 1950s and 1960s. Through her photography, she captured intimate portraits of the artists and poets in San Francisco at that time. Patricia Jordan, née Topalian, married Larry Jordan, assemblagist and avant-garde filmmaker, in the late 1950s. They lived in San Francisco, Larkspur, and finally settled in San Anselmo, California. Patricia and Larry Jordan had one daughter, Lorna, born in 1960.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives’ Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Patricia Jordan donated her papers to the Archives of American Art in 1988.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of San Francisco based Beat photographer Patricia Jordan measure 2.3 linear feet and date from 1870, 1949-1984. The papers include correspondence, much of it illustrated and with Beat artists and poets, writings, exhibition files, printed materials, photographs, and artwork.
About one-half of the collection consists of correspondence; many items of which could be considered works of art or mail art. There are letters, illustrated letters, photographs, collages, postcards, greeting and holiday cards, and exhibition invitations. Letters are addressed to Patricia Jordan, her husband Larry, and/or daughter Lorna and are from family and friends, including many Beat artists and poets such as Kenneth Anger, Steve Arnold, Paul Beattie, Wallace Berman, Stan Brakhage, Jess Collins, Joseph Cornell (with whom Larry Jordan studied in 1965), Robert Duncan, George Herms, and Gary Snyder. Family letters are from Patricia's parents, sisters, daughter, and husband Larry.
The papers contain a large number of photographs and are primarily portraits taken by Patricia Jordan of friends and family including her husband Larry, daughter Lorna, Geroge Herms, and Wallace Berman. Many of the subjects are not identified. Some photographs are candid snapshots, while others are prints and test prints of images featured in the 1975 exhibition, "A Kind of Beatness," at Focus Gallery in San Francisco.
The remainder of the collection is comprised of scattered writings, exhibition files, printed material, and artwork.
Anger, Kenneth; Beattie, Paul, 1926-; Berman, Wallace, 1926-1976; Brakhage, Stan; Cornell, Joseph; Duncan, Robert Edward, 1919-; Herms, George, 1935-; Jess, 1923-; Jordan, Larry, 1934-; Snyder, Gary, 1930-; Beat generation--California--San Francisco; Illustrated letters; Mail art; Photographers--California--San Francisco; Photographs; Women artists
- Correspondence, circa 1950s-1977; Series 1; 1.1 Linear feet Box 1, OV 4
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence comprises about one half of the collection. Many items of correspondence border on works of art, or mail art, and include letters, illustrated letters, photographs, collages, postcards, greeting and holiday cards, and exhibition invitations. Letters are addressed to Patricia, Larry, and/or Lorna Jordan from friends and family. Correspondence from friends include many artists and poets including Wallace Berman, Stan Brakhage, Joseph Cornell (with whom Larry Jordan studied in 1965), Robert Duncan, Jess Collins, George Herms, Paul Beattie, Steve Arnold, Gary Snyder, and Kenneth Anger. Some items of correspondence include revealing stories about famous beat poets. Family letters are from Patricia's parents, sisters Joanna Doyle and Dee Beattie (married to Paul Beattie), daughter Lorna, and husband Larry. One file contains corresponce between Patricia and Larry.
  - Steve Arnold, circa 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Steve Arnold, 1965-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Oversized material housed in OV 4
  - Dee and Paul Beattie, 1962-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Wallace and Shirley Berman, 1958-1975 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Joseph Cornell, 1962-1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Kirby Doyle, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Robert Duncan and Jess Collins, 1960-1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - George Herms, circa 1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - George Herms, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - George Herms, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - George Herms, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - George Herms, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - George Herms, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - George Herms, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Patricia and Larry Jordan, circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Gary and Joanne Snyder, circa 1961-circa 1962 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Family Letters and Cards, 1954-1974 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Letters and Cards, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letters, 1957-1964 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letters, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Letters, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Letters, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Postcards, 1958-1963 (Box 1, Flat-file 25)
  - Postcards, 1964-1974 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Oversized Steve Arnold correspondence from Box 1, Folder 2. (Box OV 4)
  - Oversized George Herms correspondence from Box 1, Folder 15. (Box OV 4)
  - Oversized Letters and Cards from Box 1, Folder 20. (Box OV 4)
- Writings, circa 1959-1970s; Series 2; 0.1 Linear feet Box 2
  Writings include photocopies of a mailing by Wallace Berman, a screenplay by Larry Jordan titled, "House of the Brain," and poetry manuscripts by John Wieners, Robert Duncan, Kirby Doyle, Patricia and Larry Jordan, Wallace Berman, Michael McClure, and Stan Brakhage.
  - Wallace Berman Mailings, circa 1960s (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Larry Jordan Screenplay "House of the Brain", circa 1960s (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Various Authors' Manuscripts, 1959-circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Exhibition Files, 1962-1978; Series 3; 0.1 Linear feet Box 2
  Exhibition files contain exhibition announcements, catalogs, and a handwritten list for a New York exhibition. Annoucements and catalogs relate to exhibitions that Larry, Patricia, and/or their friends were involved in.
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1962-1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, circa 1968-1975 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Exhibition List, circa 1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Printed Material, circa 1920-1984; Series 4; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  Printed material includes booklets, printed collages, a bulletin, magazines, and newspaper articles. Booklets of creative writing are by Jack Hirschman, Daniel Moore, Michael McClure, and Reverend Robert Rasmusson. A vintage booklet from the 1920s contains plates of famous paintings. Printed collages are by unidentified artists. Magazine and newspaper articles document publicity received by Patricia, Larry, or friends in Artweek, the San Francisco Chronicle, This World, and the Pacific Sun.
  - Booklet "Famous Paintings-Nudes and Semi-Nudes", circa 1920 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Booklets, 1952-1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Collages, circa 1960s (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Lomi School Bulletin, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Magazines, 1975-1983 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Articles, 1966-1984 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Photographs, circa 1870-1970s; Series 5; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 2-3
  Photographs make up another large portion of the collection (.7 linear feet; 10 folders), and are primarily portraits taken by Patricia Jordan of friends and family including her husband Larry, daughter Lorna, Geroge Herms, Wallace Berman, and many others. Many of the subjects are not identified. Some photographs are candid snapshots, while other are prints and test prints of images featured in the 1975 exhibition, "A Kind of Beatness," at Focus Gallery in San Francisco.
  Also included are vintage carte de visites, photographic collages incorporating cardboard and drawing, and photographs of Patricia Jordan, notably a triptych by Wallace Berman also featured in the Focus Gallery exhibition.
  - Carte De Visites, circa 1870 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Collages, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Friends and Family, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 15-17)
  - Lorna Jordan, circa 1960s (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Patricia Jordan, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Oversized material housed in Box 3, Folder 4
  - Oversize Friends and Family, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - Oversized Patricia Jordan from Box 2, Folder 19 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Artwork, 1949-circa 1970s; Series 6; 0.2 Linear feet Boxes 2-3
  Artwork includes sketches, prints, collages, and handmade books. Several sketches were created by Patricia's daughter Lorna. One of the handmade books was created by Robert Duncan and Jess Collins, and features many original works including drawing, collage, photography, and writing. The majority of the artworks were created by unidentified artists. Some were sent to Patricia by mail.
  - Handmade book by Robert Duncan and Jess Collins, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Handmade book by unidentified artist, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Sketches, Prints, and Collages, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Oversized Collage from Box 2, Folder 22 (Box 3, Folder 5)